Katie Roberts from Nearform.
I'm super excited to hear about this, because I'm one of those people
who basically uses AI to create new things
and then abandon them.
So what I'm interested to hear
is what Katie from Nearform has to say about brownfield codebases.
Please, big round of applause for Katie.
Hello?
Yes, hello.
I'm Katie Roberts.
You might recognize me from such tracks as the latent space,
where I've been emceeing for the last day and a half, and I'm here
to talk to you about how you can stop maintaining and start evolving.
Applying AI native engineering in brownfield code bases.
So a little bit about who I am.
I am a technical director at Nearform, where I've been for the last six years.
Prior to that, I was at the BBC, where I worked
across a variety of projects on the digital platform.
A little bit about who Nearform are, because we are one of the
sponsors of the event.
So we are a consultant services organization.
We support our our clients in solving difficult software problems.
We are hiring in case you're interested and we've got a booth downstairs.
So please do come and chat to the people down there
if you're interested to learn more about us.
So AI native engineering works.
And I know this because I've seen the numbers and on greenfield
code bases, the benefits of using AI engineering are completely undeniable.
It's a perfect place, a match made in heaven.
We can do things right from the start, being to design the product
and the architecture decisions.
They're all kept together in one spec and we can use this as a basis for our build.
We define what system should do.
We get our agents to handle the implementation.
And this means that product managers can have more input
in the development process.
We get to prototypes earlier, we get UX feedback quicker,
development teams can move faster.
We start building and testing and observable
much, much earlier in the process.
And a lot of the talks I've seen at this conference, and to be
fair, are other conferences as well tend to focus on this.
And that's also where a lot of the metrics that get reported in the press seem
to come from these type of bills.
And yeah, we've seen the same form and we're saying the same things as well.
So yeah, 80% faster kickoff.
We are able to go through our product and design process
in a much more slick, rapid and realistic way.
We've reduced our sprint zero times because we're getting our artifacts
from our discovery process, which then is bootstrapping our sprint zero.
So the timelines for that have shrunk with 50% faster to MVP.
We've seen four times development philosophy and all of this.
That means that there is much more time to focus in on some of the things
that can get lost when you're trying to build out to that MVP very quickly.
So the nonfunctional considerations are brought in from day one,
things like accessibility, security and performance.
And as Hannah Foxwell said yesterday, the velocity problem is
not really the development problem anymore.
It's we can all move a lot faster, except not all of us can,
because in the brownfield the reality is very different.
Mature code bases account for an estimated 60
to 70% of enterprise software, and they are very successful.
They're hugely successful.
That's why they've been around for five, ten, 15 years.
But with that comes accumulated technical debt,
tribal knowledge, as if you ever worked on a code base
where something was developed by somebody who's long left the organization.
And really the only the only documentation was in their head,
and they meant to write it down before they left.
Dependency. Right.
You may be falling behind
with a couple of dependencies and suddenly upgrading to the latest version
of nodes going to take two months rather than two days.
Fear driven development places in the code base where people just don't want to go.
They don't want to touch it because it's so fragile.
Test property.
And this may be an unpopular thing to say, but tests didn't always get written.
When you're under a lot of pressure.
Tests are some of those things that can get left behind, or
they become so brittle that they they're meaningless.
So integration tests and user tests with Cypress,
we've we've seen them just die off and then people ignore them.
And then there's pointless having them.
They're interdependent systems that are tightly coupled,
invisible contracts that you just can't see.
And that results in high maintenance costs.
Developers send more time deciphering the code and fixing bugs
and resolving issues than implementing new features and improvements.
Small updates become really difficult, change becomes hard.
Future development starts to crawl.
Anyone who stuck in this space as well becomes very demotivated.
And it's nobody's fault because every decision on this code
base was made with the best possible intentions.
Nobody wants the code to get like this,
and it's sometimes referred to as the ball of mud pattern.
I don't think of brownfield code as a ball of mud.
I think of them much more like a city.
A city is
very successful, and it's something that's evolved over time.
And brownfield systems tend to work like this.
They work incredibly well.
They have huge numbers of customers working on them,
and that is why they've been around for five, ten, 15 years
whilst maintaining complex user demands, whilst and all the time working
through problems like performance, security and scaling that come with that.
And like the city, they've evolved as a response to the needs
and there are areas in that functioning city.
So this is actually London.
I took this last weekend from one of the top of the skyscrapers.
I'm very pleased with this picture.
It's lovely, but you can see on this you've got paths through the city
which are very, very clear.
These are
these are the well-trodden paths, the ones that we all know where it's going.
And then there are less well maintained spaces, dead ends
and the places that you really wouldn't want to get caught in alone late at night.
So this is like your code base, and you want to evolve it into something
that is easier to build on, that's more understood,
and you get that high level view so you can start working through.
So I want to talk to you about how to evolve your
your architectures on brownfield code basis.
And I've got three different methodologies that you can have
that you can start thinking about.
If you're wanting to move your brownfield code base on to its next steps.
First off is the pseudo greenfield development,
and I think this one, I've seen this happen quite a lot.
It's really great when your legacy code base
is really coupled or fragile and developing inside it has become
very slow velocity, starting to crawl and effectively.
What you do is you branch out and say, write this new feature,
I'm going to develop it, and I'm going to treat it like a greenfield code base.
Now, when you do this, you tend to see a really fast iteration at the beginning.
You can move very, very quickly, but then you get to the point
where you're starting to merge the branch back in and things start to slow down.
It's it's really, really fantastic.
And people are doing this.
The developers who are working on it start to become kind of tourists.
They never learn about the underlying problems of the code base.
You can end up with duplication of shared concerns.
So things like authentication, logging, error handling, you may end up on your
your pseudo greenfield branch, duplicating things that the legacy system
has already solved, which means that you end up with twice
the amount of complexity because you've got diverging approaches.
The longer your greenfield branch runs in isolation,
the more the branch diverges, the more expensive it is to do
re-integration without discipline as well.
This temporary isolation
strategy can become a permanent fork, which is another problem,
and you don't really get to test
how the code is integrating well together until you get to
that last .0.4 here, merging it back into the code base.
And that means that you can end up with a huge amount of bugs
and test and refactoring as a result of that reintegration.
But it is one development pattern
and it can lead to the next one, which is the strangler fig pattern.
So what is a strangler fig?
This is always worth talking about. Strangler.
The strangler pattern was defined by Martin Fowler,
I think back in the 2000, and the idea
is that it's based on a strangler fig vine.
So the vine drops the seed and it's part of a tree, and it drops the seed
and it sends down a root opposite to what this diagram is doing.
And then it builds up self around it, slowly strangling out the nutrients
from the tree until it remains and the old tree itself is removed.
So like that, the strangle fed pattern takes away the responsibility
from the old area of code, one slice at a time.
And it's really great when you need to do
an entire system replacement alongside the original with no downtime.
This
is a pattern that's been used by Uber, Netflix, and BBC when they were evolving
to move to microservices, and it's great because it doesn't require downtimes.
If you've got a legacy system that's poorly understood,
you can intercept at the edge.
And I've used it on systems before where you've had so much dependency
that you just can't build the code on your machine anymore,
and it's the only way that you can then take the responsibility
away from something which may still be running in production,
but you actually need to evolve massive advantages.
Yeah, the code that you're writing is effectively greenfield,
but it's based on the legacy functionality.
Sorry.
And replicating.
You can leave behind the bad patterns, which is always good as well.
There's no need to touch the legacy code bases before
you create a facade which makes a boundary.
So you're keeping the old system frozen.
You're routing.
The routing layer provides a natural place for feature flags.
You can do a B testing, you can do
canary testing, you can do traffic rollback, and progress is visible.
So you can start seeing
that new traffic hitting the old system so you can test it very well.
The disadvantages with this system is that it requires
effectively setting up and running to systems.
And it's not a trivial cost in the boundary, especially for like
you've got to maintain two infrastructures effectively.
It does take some time to
work out where the points of abstraction should be, where you can
break these things apart, and it requires a commitment to completion.
There's an awful lot of half
finished strangler patterns out there where you've got some of the
some of the process has been started, some of the responsibility
has been taken away.
And then the impetus for continuing with it has been lost, which means that you're
then left with a double maintenance headache, which can be
caused a lot more stress and a lot more complexity for the teams.
So a third option is the brands by extraction.
So with branch by abstraction,
you are working from inside the code base rather than around it.
You put an interface within the code and you can then branch out
to a new implementation.
So something behind a feature flag,
so that you then can route the traffic through to your new feature flag.
It's great when you've got internal improvements
and the codes that need to remove from the area, so you can get rid of
bad patterns or rot that may have crept into your code base.
When you need to remove a deeply embedded component, this is one way to do it.
It keeps trunk releasable at all times.
The abstraction layer makes the seam explicit,
and you can easier to reason about what's old versus new.
Both implementations are active at once, so you can compare behavior on production.
So you just switch on your feature flag, check how it's working.
That means you're testing as you're going,
and that means that you're getting that constant feedback.
And it actually naturally surfaces a lot of hidden dependencies and coupling
that maybe other factors might miss the abstraction.
The disadvantages is that it is another piece of code
that you have to write and maintain and eventually delete.
There's certain code bases which are littered with these abstractions
that haven't been completely deleted, which again
adds to the cognitive complexity of the code base.
And if teams kind of lose motivation and leave these things
half finished, if you don't have a driver to complete it,
it's also quite tedious to find these things
in a large ground field code base, which is where AI can come in to help you.
And the toggle and the routing logic does add cognitive load overhead.
Like I've mentioned, it is much more like a
if you imagine a body right, and you had to replace a kidney,
if you go in there and you slice it and you remove the kidney and replace
the kidney, it's much more like that sort of methodology.
What horrible metaphor.
I'm sorry,
but you all know what I mean, don't you?
Right.
So how do we use AI to apply these methodologies?
It's tempting to think that you could just let AI loose on your code,
but AI will confidently hallucinate about your code
when autonomous
agents are deployed
into established brownfield code bases without strict guardrails, they tend
they don't really go rogue in a malicious way,
but they typically cause havoc through over optimization, generating
dart code, which passes all your tests and undermines the implicit architectural
constraints, and then creating more hidden technical debt.
I know this because as soon as I got given access
to cursor, first thing I did was like, oh, I wonder if I can refactor everything.
I did not push anything to the code base because I saw the sort of mess
it was making.
And of course it's 2026 and everybody knows that that would be a bad idea.
Surely? Nope.
It's still happening.
People are letting agents loose without bounded scopes, and it will.
It will do.
Factors that aren't tested, aren't maintainable, aren't grounded in
what the code actually did.
And as Don said in the previous talk, what you need is safety, safety, safety.
So what do I do instead?
So when I'm looking at a brownfield code base,
I don't start necessarily just with the code.
I start with listening to the developers who are working on the code.
They're the ones who are dealing with the problems that we're facing every day.
And everybody who has worked on this code base will have a view with
what is wrong with it,
how it could be improved, and some areas where it maybe shouldn't be improved.
And and this kind of harks back to Adam Tornhill.
It's quite an old book now called Your Code as a Crime scene.
And he talks about friends and investigations
and looking at how you can do forensics across your code base.
And this is just one piece of evidence.
Your your developers are excellent eyewitnesses.
We did for the I work fully remote, so we did it as a miro exercise.
Everybody had an opinion.
We created a graph of value versus complexity.
And we allowed everybody to to bring to the table as we think these are areas
where there could be opportunities for us to technically improve our code base.
And then from there,
we started focusing AI around those problems.
And we started to rather than do it as one big process,
we focused down based on where the areas that we knew were problems.
So, for example, we knew that there was a significant amount
of dead code within our backend code base.
We focused in our coastal investigations to look at those.
We looked for dead code paths, we looked for duplication,
we looked for pattern inconsistencies, and we we looked for complexity hotspots.
We even did some OWASP-style scanning, but
we wouldn't say that's not to replace doing proper security scanning.
It just gave us a sort of high level.
These are areas of where your code base has got a bit smelly over time.
And we started generating some dependency graphs.
We started generating some maps of what the code is doing now,
not what our documentation said the code was doing, because documentation
has always been something that every developer loves to update regularly.
So yeah, it does.
It rots over time and we know that.
And the one thing that we found is that this process
was made significantly faster.
It still needs to be human reviewed because yes, AI will confidently
hallucinate about your code base,
but it did mean that something very, very interesting happened.
We had some objective data, and we found that
when we had that data that people would look at it.
They were it wasn't written by
the cleverest person on the team.
It was written by AI.
So we had more people were willing to put in a view on
this is right, this is wrong.
I have observed something, whereas previously you might have seen
the principal engineer on the team would say, I think this is right
and everyone would just follow what they were saying.
It was really good for that.
It also helped the break the bike shed, the bike shedding bottleneck.
So where everybody goes, this is what I think is wrong.
This is what I think is wrong.
And then there's just a fight about what is
what is the best thing to work on first.
We now had some objective data that we could say we can actually see.
We've got metrics that we can start looking at.
We know where our coverage gaps are.
And it gave us a way to prioritize the work that we needed to do,
and it gave us a destination we wanted to work towards.
So yeah,
core principles for working in the brownfield development.
Don't trust the AI input.
Brown blindly work in small scopes.
Try to keep it focused down. Yeah.
Remembering that you want to people to read this afterwards version
control everything.
I mean you don't want to
be pushing anything up to your code bases without version control.
Creates findings backlog and then prioritize your findings backlog.
You can work through that as time goes on.
Create human readable docs.
This needs to be reviewed and understood by the team and the whole team.
So make sure that you've got something that you can go back to
and understand, and then put your guardrails in place.
Tests, logs, static code analysis.
We spent a lot of time before we did any of the actual implementation
work, making sure that things like our SonarQube
was up, running, working, and reporting as we expected to do.
Not what, and made sure that we had confidence in the test suites that we had.
And then once we did that, we decided to focus on one area at a time.
So we used a you can either do that by specific feature
requirement or specific technical requirement.
And we made sure that we called out things that we found as we went as well.
So we have rules that make sure that our
our skills don't repeat bad patterns that we have in the code base.
It's very, very easy to go, oh, I see it's done it like this.
I'll just do it like that again.
We make sure that there are
there's a clear definition of
we want to see more like this, a pattern, less like that pattern.
And we keep those skills alongside our code.
Now some examples.
This is a pseudo greenfield approach.
And it just gives you an idea of
of what we've actually done at near form and how powerful this can be.
So yes, it feels like six months worth of scope was shipped in eight weeks.
This is. It's an amazing statistic.
We used to estimate spectrum of development on this.
And we.
The parts that were were really useful on this is
there was a huge amount of product requirements
that had been produced but never, never actually implemented.
So we used the AI to go through those and then create the process
to do this with reverse engineering the product,
reverse-engineered the product requirements from that documentation,
and we reduced the time there from months to a week.
We did a detailed code base mapping, reverse engineered the documentation from
the existing code base to the AI context that reduced from two weeks to hours
and automated the story mapping from the PRD creation.
Creating the Jura tickets.
And this is, this is something that it's always worth
putting a little bit of time into, creating a skill that creates really good.
It's that anyone can pick up with a,
because it just means that you can parallelize your work so much better.
And the impact was
that the faster time to market six months work in
eight weeks, four times faster than the than one of our competitors had estimated.
So that's nice.
But like I said, pseudo-greenfield isn't right for every project.
It was right for this one branch by abstraction.
So this is a code base that I'm a little bit closer to.
And it's it's 5000 lines.
Oh, sorry, 500,000 lines of code.
So half a million lines of code.
It's tightly coupled distributed monolith.
It's a large legacy brownfield
architecture that we inherited from another supplier.
Again, this is the kind of thing that happens all the time in in the enterprise.
The whole of the old development team may have disappeared.
So you don't have that story of why it has been built up like this.
There wasn't architectural decision records,
there was a limited number of tests on it. And
it this sounds really simple,
but all we wanted to do was update
the latest version of AG Grid for the use of the latest features,
and what we discovered when we tried to do this the first time
was that the grids had been implemented individually,
without an inheritance pattern and no shared abstraction.
So this meant that when we try to do the very first time
we upgraded ag grid, it took us a significant amount of time.
I don't actually have the metrics.
I think it was about a month.
And you think that's just upgrading
from one version to another, and then because of that,
you then have a problem of, well, how do we then move forward with this?
How do we get better?
You can't have that.
That's a complete time sink.
We can't keep having that time sink because all of these these things like ag
grid, they're rapidly evolving now, especially with AI on their side too.
So we don't want to be left behind.
We don't want to keep in this this space.
We want to be able to use this. So
what we did was we created a plan.
And this is, I think, another difference between Green and Banfield code
bases in a greenfield build
a discovery process is is kind of expected.
We expect to do a bit of discovery.
We expect to do a bit of planning.
We expect to have a think about what we're building before we actually build it
in a brownfield.
It's often let's all just dive in and just get this done mentality.
And that can mean that the planning stage is forgotten and something that whilst
we've been starting to move towards a more AI native way of working,
the plan phase has extended and we are putting more time
into our planning because we want to do the proper archeology on the code base,
because we want to make sure that we're calling out the good path,
and because we want to make sure we've got structured roadmap.
And from that, we then created something called a plan skill,
which is all the technical and product considerations captured.
And then the work was broken down by that great
component skill that we created.
And then this is then handed off to our developer skill.
The developer skill
has it's a multi-agent flow.
So the orchestrator agent analyzes the requirements.
And then it sends off various different agents to do a check.
Build a test scaffolding.
Another agent does that.
It looks at what's the implementation.
It does static analysis and quality gates.
And then it uses another agent to do a review of its own work
before pushing it to the developer to do a human review of the work before
pushing it to a full human in the loop sign
off to go through to the
to the main development pipeline, and then once
it's done that, it then goes back and updates the master plan.
So if you think we've got to do
80 of these, you want to you want to do this right a few times.
And then we've got a process now.
So it starts out relatively it was relatively slow to start out.
So the first couple of these took a decent amount of time.
So that as we work through the skill, getting it right, making sure it was
robust, but we're seeing a flywheel effect with velocity improvements.
We're starting to push these things through much, much quicker.
And it's easier for the developers to run these almost in the background.
They they can just keep going.
And another halo effect from this is that we are starting to build up
a library of skills within our code base that we can then refer back to.
This is what good looks like for a skill development.
This is how you the process that we're using for the skill.
This is how we want to work.
And that is then leveraging other areas of the code
base that we can then start moving into improving.
And we're starting to get, like I say, flywheel effect of velocity improvement
as we go.
This is my practical
takeaway slide, because I think that it's always good to be able to just remember,
what's good about doing this is start with a math, not a migration.
Always start with thinking about what you need to do.
Let your spec be the contract, making sure
that you're thinking about what it is you want to build up front.
That planning phase is is so important.
Making sure that you're building the right thing,
thinking slices and not rewrites
do things in small chunks, because if you're chunking down the work,
it's much, much easier for you to get through it.
And you'll get to the point of, yeah, that's done, let's move on to the next.
And complexity is the opportunity.
It's it's
something where I think we can really, really lean into in the brownfield.
It does take a little bit longer, but once you're working
in this way you start seeing results very, very quickly.
So there you go.
That's how how you can use AI to start paying down your technical debt.
Thank you very much, Katie Roberts.
Any questions at all?
One question.
Where is lunch?
Yeah, I know I'm standing you between you and food.
That's. Yeah.
That's especially there's a kitchen just here and I can smell it.
So thank you all. Thank you again, Katie.
Big round of applause.
Sorry. There's a question. Oh.
There's a there's a question. One final question.
You're not moving.
Any of you.
Thank you for a really great presentation.
One thing that I want to know is how do you divide the skills
between different feature teams?
How do we divide the skills within the different feature teams?
If you like a monolith.
So we do it.
We slice it at the epic level.
So what you would
normally have as an epic, we then slice that and give those to our feature teams.
And then it might be our feature teams are very much smaller to work through those.
So instead of being like 4 or 5 people, we can now do that with 1 or 2 people
so that they are working through with their agents,
and that seems to be working quite well at the moment.
There is always you've got to be careful that you don't end up with gills
diverging as well. So there has to be some,
collaboration making sure that across the feature teams
you're doing them in the same way and that people are reviewing
still what's going on.
So you're not building silos of skills.
Thank you.
Thanks very much.
Okay. Class dismissed.
See you back again.
After lunch. All